Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo collection on Latin American Folklore
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
- Mendes, Eunice Evanira Pereira. Contribuição para o estudo da modinha. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/119)
  Origins and examples of modinha, popular songs in Brazil.
- Mendoza, Vicente T. El Folklore en Mexico: 1946-1949. México, 1950. (Box-item 5/120)
  A short overview of the various initiatives and publications that were created to preserve and collect Mexican folklore between 1946 and 1949.
- Mendoza, Vicente T. La música tradicional española en México. Mexico, 1953. (Box-item 5/121)
  A short study about traditional Spanish music in Mexico.
- Mendoza, Vicente T. 1894-1964. La música tradicional 4. Mexico: FCE, no date. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/122)
  Research about the origins of traditional Mexican music prior to the arrival of the Spaniards with musical examples.
- Ministério da Educação e Cultura, Departamento de Assuntos Culturais, Fundação Nacional de Arte, Campanha de Defesa do Folclore Brasileiro. Bibliografia Folclórica 4 (1979): 3-31. (Box-item 5/123)
  Bibliography of publications related to different aspects of Brazilian folklore such as beliefs, language, arts, and music, among others.
- Ministério da Educação e Cultura – Campanha de Defesa do Folclore Brasileiro. Congresso Nacional do Samba. Carta do Samba, aprovada pelo I Congresso Nacional do Samba, 28de novembro/2 de dezembro de 1962. 1962. (Box-item 5/124)
  Discussion of the problems of the evolving tradition of samba music in Brazil.
- Ministério da Educação e Cultura Secretaria da Cultura Fundação Nacional de Arte, Instituto Nacional do Folclore. Folclore Paranaense: Exposição – de 21 de Agosto a 29 de Novembro de 1981. 1981. (Box-item 5/125)
  This book describes a governmental initiative to give exposure to the different folklore manifestations of the state of Paraná in Brazil.
- Miranda, Nicanor. O Congresso Internacional de Folclore. São Paulo, 1940. (Box-item 5/126)
  A summary of the activities and goals of the International Congress of Folklore in 1940. The pamphlet includes some examples of folkloric expressions from other parts of the world written in languages other than Portuguese.
- Mussolini, Gioconda.. Os "pasquins" do litoral norte de São Paulo e suas peculiaridades na Ilha de São Sebastião 1950. (Box-item 5/127)
  Pasquim is an old tradition in which a person would recite verses that he would create about different subjects and the audience would repeat. Considered mostly an oral tradition, pasquins represent the folkloric expression of the population living on the north coast of São Paulo. This study about the pasquins also includes the practice of the tradition on São Sebastião Island and along the coast of São Paulo.
- Natal: Departamento de Imprensa. Estatutos da Sociedade Brasileira de Folk-lore. 1949. (Box-item 5/128)
  This short book lists the statutes of the Brazilian Society of Folklore.
- Neves, Guilherme Santos. "Bandas de Congos." Cadernos de Folclore. 30 (no date): 3-32. (Box-item 5/129)
  This publication describes the origin, the musical instruments, and lyrics related to Bandas de Congos in the state of Espírito Santo, Brazil. The name Bandas de Congo refers to congo, an Afro-Brazilian name for the main musical instrument of this tradition, the drum.
- Oliveira, Clovis de. André da Silva Gomes (1752-1844): "O Mestre de Capela da Sé de São Paulo" – Obra premiada no Concurso de História promovido pelo Departamento Municipal de Cultura, de São Paulo, em 1946. Cidade de São Paulo, 1954. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 5/130)
  A biography of André da Silva Gomes, an important musician in the state of São Paulo who, among other things, founded the first choir of the Sé Cathedral.
- O.N.D.A. Rosa de Ouro. Rio de Janerio, no date. (Box-item 5/131)
  Rosa de Ouro was a musical program produced by Kleber Santos for a youth theatre in Rio de Janeiro featuring popular carioca (the city of Rio de Janeiro) music. This program from the performance contains short biographies of the performers.
- Pacheco, Jacy. O cantor da vila: Documentos e episódios inéditos de vida de Nöel. Rio de Janeiro: Edições Minerva, 1958. (Box-item 5/132)
  A biography of Noel Rosa, a significant name in the Brazilian popular music of Rio de Janeiro during the 1950s. The book, written by Rosa's cousin, includes lyrics, pictures, and curiosities about the composer and singer.
- Pardo Tovar, Andrés. Los cantares tradicionales del Baudo. Bogotá, 1960. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 6/133)
  Documentation of traditional music of the region of Baudo in Colombia.
- Pardo Tovar, Andrés y Jesús Pinzón Urrea. Rítmica y melódica del folclor chocoano. Bogotá, 1961. (Box-item 6/134)
  Documentation of the rhythm and melodies of the folklore of the province of Choco in Colombia.
- Parreira, Roberto; Vicente Salles; Fundação Nacional de Arte. Artesanto brasileiro. Rio de Janeiro: Edição FUNARTE, 1978. (Box-item 6/135)
  An overview of the techniques and materials used in Brazilian handicrafts.
- Pereira Salas, Eugenio. La música de la Isla de Pascua. Santiago de Chile: Instituto de Investigaciones Musicales, [Inscribed.] 1947. (Box-item 6/136)
  Salas offers a synthesis of the meaning of music in the spiritual life of the people who live on Easter Island off the coast of Chile (Isla de Pascua).
- Piazza, Walter F. O Quicumbí. Florianópolis: Comissão Catarinense de Folklore, 1954. (Box-item 6/137)
  This publication details the movements, musical instruments, and lyrics related to the Quicumbí, a folkloric dance with African roots. The material was collected in Cachoeira, a small community in Florianópolis, Brazil.
- Pimentel, Altimar de Alencar. "Barca da Paraíba." Cadernos de Folclore 25 (no date): 3-71. (Box-item 6/138)
  This publication describes the dramatic dance, of maritime origin, performed in the state of Paraíba, Brazil. The participants of this tradition push a barge from their headquarters to the front of the city's main church, and there, they sing songs and pray.
- Pinto, Alexina de Magalhães. Cantigas das creanças e do povo e dansas populares. Rio de Janeiro: F. Alves, 1916. (Box-item 6/139)
  A selection of mostly anonymous popular songs divided by categories, such as general songs, songs of the black people, songs and dances, etc.
- Piza, Flávio de Toledo. Estudo sobre o romance do soldado jogador. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 6/140)
  Using the version from the state of Minas Gerais of the poem "O Jogador na Igreja," Flávio Piza examines different aspects of this oral tradition. He also adds to his study the version of the same poem from other states in Brazil and from other countries, such as Argentina.
- Plath, Oreste. Alimentación y lenguaje popular. Santiago de Chile, 1949. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 6/141)
  A collection of popular vocabulary related to food in Chile.
- Plath, Oreste. Folklore Chileno: Aspectos populares infantiles. Santiago de Chile: La Universidad de Chile, 1946. (Box-item 6/142)
  A study of children's folklore in Chile with analysees of songs, last names, and short stories that never end.
- Prado, José Nascimento de Almeida. Baile Pastoril no Sertão da Bahia. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, [Inscribed.] 1951. (Box-item 6/143)
  Monograph on the pastoral dances of the backlands in the state of Bahia, Brazil.
- Prado, José Nascimento de Almeida. Trabalhos fúnebres na roça. São Paulo: Departamento de cultura, 1947. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 6/144)
  A collection of songs, prayers, and rituals involving the death and funerals of people in the southern area of São Paulo, Brazil.
- Querino, Manoel. Artistas bahianos: Indicações biographicas. Bahia: Officinas da Empreza "A Bahia," 1911. (Box-item 6/145)
  Short biographies of artists, painters, sculptors, and musicians from the state of Bahia, Brazil.
- Ramon Paradela, Emilio. "Un vinten p'al Judas:" Contribución al folklore de Montevideo. Montevideo: Centre de Estudios Folklóricis del Uruguay, 1965. (Box-item 6/146)
  The author of Un vinten p'al Judas explores the origin of the tradition of burning an effigy of Judas Iscariot in Latin America.
- Ramón y Rivera, Luis Felipe. Problemas de la grabación y transcripción musical de los tambores. Separata del II Tomo de Actas del XXXIII Congreso Internacional de Americanistas Celebrado en San José de Costa Rica del 20 al 27 de Julio de 1958 Impreso por la editorial Lehmann, no date. [Inscribed on cover.] (Box-item 6/147)
  A discussion of the problems involved in the recording and transcription of drum music.
- Ramón y Rivera, Luis Felipe. Supervivencia de la Polifonia Popular en Venezuela. Separata del II Tomo de Actas del XXXIII Congresso Internacional de Americanistas Celebrado en San José de Costa Rica del 20 al 27 de Julio de 1958 Impresso por la editorial Lehmann, no date. (Box-item 6/148)
  A discussion of the support for the preservation of the cantos polifónicos from Venezuela.
- Ramón y Rivera, Luis Felipe. Una interpretación psicológica del coplero popular. Caracas, 1953. [Inscribed on cover.] (Box-item 6/149)
  A psychological interpretation of the copla, a poetic composition that, in general, is formed by four verses, and is the root of popular songs.
- Ramon y Rivera, Luis Felipe. "Aspectos del culto de Maria Lionza en el Distrito Bruzual, Estado Yaracuy." Boletín indigenista venezolano. 6 (1958): 127-130. (Box-item 6/150)
  In this study, Luis Felipe Rivera reveals some of the elements associated with the myth of Maria Lionza in the Bruzual District of the state of Yaracuy in Venezuela. According to this myth, Maria Lionza appears to people and then performs favors in exchange for their souls.
- Rangel, Welmann Galvão de França. Algumas contribuições espanholas ao folclore paulista. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 6/151)
  In this book, Rangel observes the Spanish influence on the folklore of the Catanduva area in the city of São Paulo, Brazil.
- Revista Sertaneja no. 19 (1959): 3-70. [Note pages 31 and 48.] (Box-item 6/152)
  Sertaneja is a magazine that circulated between 1958-1959 in São Paulo and promoted the sertaneja (rural) music, singers, and stories of the provincial life in Brazil. There are notes on the cover of the magazine that point to two articles within the magazine. The first article, Conferido a Alceu Maynard Araújo o prêmio "Brasiliana," is an interview with the Brazilian folklorist Alceu Maynard whose work was chosen to receive the Brasiliana award. The second article, Sebastião das Dores O Fandangueiro, was written by Alceu Maynard Araújo and describes the life of Sebastião Manuel dos Santos, a viola player known for his performances of the fandango in Itanhaém, São Paulo. The article also describes some of the typical dances and traditions of Itanhaém, such as Volta-Senhora and Pica-Pau.
- Ribeiro, Darcy. Notícia dos ofaié-chavante. São Paulo, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 6/153)
  A short description of the time Darcy Ribeiro spent with the last two families of the indigenous group of Ofaié, who lived in the south of the state of Mato Grosso, Brazil.
- Ribeiro, Luis da Silva. "Influência Portuguesa no Adagiário Gaúcho." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científíca e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 11 (1957): 32-52. (Box-item 7/154)
  Discusses the Portuguese influence on the Adagiário Gaúcho from Rio Grande do Sul. Adagiário is a type of popular sentence, saying, or a proverb.
- Ribeiro, Maria de Lourdes Borges. Um grupo de moçambique de Aparecida do Norte. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 7/155)
  This study describes the tradition of Moçambique within a particular group living in the district of São Roque in Aparecida do Norte, São Paulo. Besides detailing the dance, its movements and songs, the book includes many illustrations of the moçambique tradition.
- São Paulo, Brazil (State). Departamento Estadual de Informações. Cadernos de folklore 1, 1947. (Box-item 7/156)
  A collection of popular poems from the city of São Paulo, Brazil.
- Schmidt, Carlos Borges. O pão da terra. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 7/157)
  The history and usage of the manioc, a starchy root vegetable that is commonly used in Brazilian cooking.
- Shaffer, Kay. O berimbau-de-barriga e seus Toques. Rio de Janeiro: Ministério da Educação e Cultura, Secretaria de Assuntos Culturais, Fundação Nacional de Arte, and Instituto Nacional do Folclore, 1976. (Box-item 7/158)
  The berimbau is a stringed musical instrument associated with the Afro-Brazilian martial art of capoeira. In this book, Shaffer explains the origin, the history, and the present use of this instrument in Bahia, Brazil.
- Silva, Alcionilio Brüzzi Alves da. Discoteca etno-linguístico-musical das tribos dos rios Uaupés, Içana e Cauáburi. [Inscribed.]São Paulo: Centro de Pesquisas de Iauareté, 1961. (Box-item 7/159)
  A description of the traditional celebrations, music, musical instruments and general habits of the Indian tribes of the river Uaupés.
- Silva, José Calasans Brandão da. O sebastianismo no folclore de Canudos. Bahia: Artes Gráficas, 1959. (Box-item 7/160)
  A brief study about the influence of Sebastianismo in the folkore of the Canudos community in the state of Bahia, Brazil. Sebastianismo is a mystic movement that started in Portugal after the death of King Sebastião, and was used by a popular religious leader, Antonio Conselheiro, to convince the population of Canudos in Brazil to follow him. The Canudos movement exploded in war on November 1896, after the proclamation of Brazil as a republic in 1889. The conflict between Antonio Conselheiro's followers and the government led to the complete destruction of the Canudos community.
- Simon, Michel. "A Propos Des "Danses Dramatiques" Brésiliennes." Théâtre D'aujord'hui, special issue (January – February 1959): 10-14. [Inscribed, p. 10.] (Box-item 7/161)
  This publication contains an essay about the elements of dance within the Brazilian folk traditions of pastoris, chenganças, and reisados.
- Siqueira, Baptista. Folclore humorístico. Rio de Janeiro, 1946. (Box-item 7/162)
  A collection of many short stories that have the same main character, Aleixo. In the northeast of Brazil, Aleixo became the name for any hero who never gives up, like Don Quijote de la Mancha.
- Soares, Luci de Lourdes. "Notas a Lapis sôbre a Arqueologia Norte-Rio-Grandense." Coleção Mossoroense XV ser. B. no. 381 (1982): 3-32 (Box-item 7/163)
  Observations about the archeology of the indigenous groups of Amerabas in the state of Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil. The book contains a map of distribution of these groups and photographs of artifacts and archeological findings.
- Sociedad Folklórica de México. Anuario de la Sociedad Folklorica de Mexico 3 (1942): 7-204. (Box-item 7/164)
  Scholarly journal with articles on the definition of folklore, traditional games from Puerto Rico, and legends of the Zapotecas, an indigenous group from Mexico.
- Sociedad Folklórica de México. Anuario de la Sociedad Folklorica de Mexico 6 (1945): 213-408. (Box-item 7/165)
  Scholarly journal with articles on poems, popular beliefs, and dances of Mexico.
- Sociedad Folklórica de México. Anuario de la Sociedad Folklorica de Mexico 6 (1950): 415-557. (Box-item 7/166)
  Scholarly journal with articles on traditional food, customs, and celebrations of Mexico.
- Sociedad Folklórica de México. Anuario de la Sociedad Folklorica de Mexico 7 (1951): 7-142. (Box-item 7/167)
  Scholarly journal with articles on songs, poems, and beliefs of Mexico.
- Society of Ethnomusicology. Ethnomusicology 11 no. 3 (1967): 267-292. (Box-item 7/168)
  This publication focuses on the music of the Tepehua tribe that is played during a ceremony called Halakiltúnti. These textless songs, during the Halakiltunti ritual, are believed to cure psychosomatic illness, secure rain, and restore harmony to daily life in the tribe.
- Souza, Yvonildo de. Influência negra na música brasileira. Recife: Editora Nordeste, 1953. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 7/169)
  A short study of the African influence on the music of Brazil.
- Spalding, Walter. "A Historia e o Povo: Costumes, Poesia e Lendas." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científíca e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 8 (1956): 67-101. (Box-item 7/170)
  Walter Spalding describes some of the popular poems, customs, and legends of the state of Rio Grande do Sul that were influenced by the history of Brazil.
- Spalding, Walter. "Bibliografia do Folclore Rio Grandense do Sul." Comissão Nacional de Folclore do I.B.E.C.C. Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura – Comissão Brasileira da Organização Educacional, Científica e Cultural das Nações Unidas (UNESCO) no. 4 (1954): 245-263. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 7/171)
  A bibliography of publications about folklore in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Spalding, Walter. Tradições gaúchas. Pôrto Alegre: Edição da Comissão Sul-Riograndense de Folclore, 1957. (Box-item 7/172)
  A description of the origin, traditions, and poems from the state of Rio Grande do Sul related to three elements, the house, the salt, and the rain.
- Thieblot, Marcel Jules. Fumo e Fumeiros no Brasil: Prequisa sôbre os plantadores de tabaco e os artesões do fumo nas regiões de São Paulo, Minas Gerais, Bahia (Recôncavo) Amazônia (Rondônia e Pará). São Paulo: Brasileira de Folclore, 1988. (Box-item 7/173)
  Research on the culture of the tobacco plantation in the Brazilian states of São Paulo, Minas Gerais, Bahia, Rondônia, and Pará.
- Thompson, Stith. "Folklore in South America." Reprinted from Journal of American Folklore, 1948. (Box-item 7/174)
  A report of Thompson's trip to South America in 1948. He describes the folklorists he met and their field of work in the South American countries he visited, Bolivia, Argentina, and Brazil.